<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter written by a French Catholike gentleman, to the maisters at Sorbonne. Concerning the late victories obtained by the king of Nauarre, aswell against the Duke of Ioyeuse at Coutras vpon Tuesday the twentieth of October, 1587. as els where</title>
            <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07765</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18144</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107518</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843217</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843217</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7932</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07765)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7932)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 480:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter written by a French Catholike gentleman, to the maisters at Sorbonne. Concerning the late victories obtained by the king of Nauarre, aswell against the Duke of Ioyeuse at Coutras vpon Tuesday the twentieth of October, 1587. as els where</title>
                  <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>78, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe for Edward Aggas, and are to be sold at his shope at the West end of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by STC to Philippe de Mornay.</note>
                  <note>Includes, at end, "The King of Nauars song after his victorie".</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through,.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  IV, --  King of France, 1553-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Henry III, 1574-1589 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Coutras (France) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7932:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7932:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> LETTER Written by a French Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>gentleman, to the</hi> Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters at Sorbonne.</p>
            <p>CONCERNING <hi>the late victories obtained by the</hi> King of Nauarre, aſwell againſt the Duke of Ioyeuſe at Coutras vpon Tueſday the twentieth of October. 1587. as els where.</p>
            <p>LONDON <hi>Printed by Iohn Wolfe</hi> for Edward Aggas, and are to be ſold at his ſhope at the Weſt end of Paules. 1588.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:7932:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:7932:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER WRIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by a French Catholike <hi>gentleman, to the maiſters of</hi> Sorbonne at Paris: Concerning the late victories obtained by the king of Nauarre aſwell againſt the Duke of Ioyeuſe at Coutras vpon tueſday the twentieth of October. 1587. as els where.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y maiſters, I ſhal not be, as I thinke, the firſt Reporter of the lamentable newes of the death of the Duke of <hi>Ioyeuſe,</hi> and the ouerthrow of his whole Armie: and ſo conſequently may reioyce that I ſhall not be the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of your heauineſſe, albeit I will not neuertheleſſe faile in the diſcharge of my duetie, neither bee the laſt that ſhall giue you aduice vpon ſo ſtraunge an accident, to the end to teſtifie vnto you, that for my owne part I bewaile this publike calamitie, howbeit, not ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7932:3"/>as to deſpaire of whatſoeuer this heauy day hath left vs, but rather to ſéeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the moſt firme and ſtedfaſt kinde of hope, that we may and ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue, to the ende to bring forth the peace of this miſerable realme. In as much therefore as your ſelues are the moſt notable company among whome the principall point of the eſtate, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly religion, is intreated vpon, I doe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect my ſelfe eſpecially to you, to the end you may iudge of my zeale, and if any profit may be taken thereof, you may impart the ſame to thoſe that ſtill harken after you for the vnderſtanding of their ſaluation: alſo that it may bee the foundation whereupon againe to build vp our ruines to the common re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of the people, and the diſcharge of your conſciences. But before I come to theſe remedies, I will lay open vnto you the new wounds that we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued in the late battaile of <hi>Coutras</hi> the twentieth of this moneth by the King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> with the aſſiſtance of the Lords the prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Turen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, Trimouille,</hi> and other Lords and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7932:3"/>gentlemen their partakers. The ſaide King being returned from <hi>Monſoreau</hi> where he had happely ſoiorned for the ſpace of fiftéene dayes or more after the ouerthrow of the troupes of the late D. of <hi>Ioyeuſe,</hi> and the Marqueſſe of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi> as they retired from their voyage of <hi>Poictou,</hi> alſo hauing through the conduct of the L. of <hi>Turenne</hi> ſeaſed vpon the rich carriages of the D. of <hi>Mercoeur</hi> neare to <hi>Saumeur,</hi> who was comming out of his gouernment of <hi>Bretagne</hi> to ioyne with his brother in law, the ſaide D. of <hi>Ioyeuſe</hi> yet being at <hi>Tours,</hi> and withall had receyued the ſaide L. Earle of <hi>Soiſſons</hi> with all his troupes: after (I ſay) that the ſaid king was thus vpon his return &amp; led had his armie into <hi>Sainctonge,</hi> he tooke two Cannons from <hi>Rochell,</hi> and in the end determined to march into <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcogne</hi> as well for the reenforcing of his troupes, as to ioyne with his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine power vpon the borders of thoſe prouinces that fauored him. Now becauſe, as you know, that that was the onely thing which the K. did moſt feare, he gaue charge to the ſaid D. of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7932:4"/>
               <hi>Ioyeuſe</hi> to ſtoppe this his courſe by all meanes poſſible, yea if all other oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities failed, not to ſpare the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of the battaile, which he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke to performe, and to the ſame end marched with thoſe troupes which hee had before, together with the other that his maieſtie had newly graunted him, as well for the better ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as to baniſh from him all feare of thoſe that the K. of <hi>Nauarre</hi> did leade. The ground of this enterpriſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in the paſſage ouer the riuers of <hi>Droune</hi> and <hi>L'Iſle,</hi> and the moſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to feaze thereon was to preſcribe law to the more ſlothfull. In reſpect hereof the ſaide D. of <hi>Ioyeuſe</hi> after he had a while at the héeles followed and coſted the K. of <hi>Nauarre</hi> his armie, in the end fet forwarde towarde <hi>Roche-Chalays,</hi> entending according to the good aduiſe giuen him by the L. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal</hi> of <hi>Matignon</hi> to ſeaze vpon <hi>Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tras,</hi> which was the place of moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, in reſpect of the ſituation ſo fauourable to the paſſage ouer <hi>Droun,</hi> but he loſt his time by reaſon that as his light horſemen were ariued and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7932:4"/>their lodgings, the K. of <hi>Nauarres</hi> being the ſtronger came vpon them, and became maiſters thereof on Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day night the nyntenth of October. Thus beſides the ſaid kinges diligence which is the moſt neceſſarie parte in warrelike attempts, and the thing that hath bred him great credit among his partakers, his force was alſo preiudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid D. of <hi>Ioyeuſe:</hi> who neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles being deſirous to yeeld al dueties of obedience to his maiſters comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, and imagining that the K. of <hi>Nauarre</hi> being incloſed betweene the two riuers, might be eaſily ouercome, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the next day to giue him bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faile, and to the ſame end appointed his whole armie their méeting place betweene <hi>Roche-Chalays</hi> and <hi>Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tras,</hi> whither hee came earely in the morning, at leaſure and without anie impeachment of the ſaid kings troupes, and tooke his battaile ground within halfe a league of <hi>Coutras</hi> to his moſt aduantage poſſible. The K. of <hi>Nauarre</hi> as I was informed, hauing the firſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſement thereof earely enough in the morning, ſtayed vntil he had alſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7932:5"/>the ſecond yea and the third before hee woulde once ſtirre, albeit hee made no leſſe ſhew to be deſirous of battaile than our ſelues: And in déed he had giuen vs occaſion twiſe before, which wee found not to hee for our aduantage. Howbeit, ſo ſoone as the ſaide K. was by theſe diuers reportes aſſures there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, he tooke horſe, and departing from <hi>Coutras,</hi> went to méete the ſaide D. of <hi>Ioyeuſe,</hi> ſet his armie in hattaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray, and in the meane time comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the L. of <hi>Clermont</hi> maiſter of his ordinance to paſſe it ouer vnto his ſide of the riuer, which hee cold not doe the day before. Then hauing brought it into the fore front, he ſo ordered it that without anoying any of his own part, about eight of the clocke it played for eight or nine belees verie conueniently vpon the firſt ſquadron of oure horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and ſo carried away a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our gentlemen, which made the reſt to reſolue rather to goe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charge, then ſo miſerably to dye without anie fight. Thus about nyne of the clock our light horſemen with foure, hundreth horſe gaue vpon the K. of <hi>Nauarres,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:7932:5"/>which after ſome blowes, was in the end ſhaken and our men made glaſſe windowes therein: the reſt of the ſaide kinges army conſiſted of foure ſquare battailes, whereof that of the L. of <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renne</hi> was ſmelt to by the L. of <hi>Lauer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine.</hi> The other thrée wherin were the thrée princes of the blood, kéeping their ſtanding did behold the ioyning, and by and by after the D. of <hi>Ioyeuſe</hi> marched furiouſly to the charge for the generall conflict, whereto theſe three Princes each in the face of his ſquadron came a ſoft pace, only vpon the trot as cloſe and with as good aſſurance as euer I ſee me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of warre martch. When they came to handy blowes, our men ſodenly turned their backes, whether it were that the ſpeares ſtopped them at the ſtrait of the conflict, or that we were reencountered ſomewhat rudely. Finally, the fight was ſharpe and ſo violent that it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued the leſſe while, and as warres are vncertaine, the whole victorie remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the king of <hi>Nauarre.</hi> And it is a maruellous matter that by ten of the clocke neuer a one of our men ſtood to the ſight, neither ſo much as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7932:6"/>in the field, which lay couered with a great number of the dead, and thoſe very notable. Such as eſcaped the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie of the weapone, either fledde with ſhame, or fell into their enemies handes, ſome wounded and ſome not, whereas in ſo notable an ouerthrow there were loſt on the king of <hi>Nauars</hi> part very few, and not ſo much as any one of name or commaundement: but of our part all the Captaines were ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wounded or ſlaine or taken, beſtoos the D. of <hi>Ioyenſe</hi> the Generall, whoſe only loue might ſuffice to make vs ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to lament, as for ſuch a miſhap as hath ſtriken a ſhrewde blow at ſuch of our affaires as were ordered and ſet vp again by the king vnder the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of his fortune. Howbeit it is alſo replemiſhed to infinite other our loſſes, whereby we haue the leſſe meanes left to helpe vs to riſe againe from ſo miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a fall. I will name vnto you the moſt notable of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I can remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that are ſlaine, to the end that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering of them, you may the better contemplate this miſhappe which ſhall peraduenture be but the way to many
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7932:6"/>more whereunto we doo runne, if God withhold vs not.</p>
            <p>Amongſt our dead there are beſides the D. of <hi>Ioyeuſe,</hi> the L. of Saint <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> his brother, the L. of <hi>Breſſay</hi> who carried the white Cornet. The L. of <hi>Ronſay</hi> the yonger <hi>Pienne Guidon</hi> to the ſaid D. of <hi>Ioyeuſe.</hi> The Earles of <hi>Suze, Gouuelo, &amp; Aubigeou,</hi> the L. of <hi>Fumell,</hi> the L. of <hi>Neufuy</hi> the elder of <hi>Perigord, Croyſet</hi> ſonne to the L. of <hi>Rochfort,</hi> the L. of <hi>Gurat</hi> Cornet of <hi>Maumont,</hi> The L. of S. <hi>Fort</hi> Guidon to the L. of S. <hi>Luc.</hi> The L. of <hi>Vaux</hi> Lieutenant to the L. of <hi>Bellegarde.</hi> The L. of <hi>Montignyes</hi> Enſigne, <hi>Tier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celin</hi> maiſter of the field, <hi>Chenet</hi> his chiefe Captaine, <hi>Vallade</hi> one of his Captaines, Captain <hi>Baccullard,</hi> yong <hi>Campels,</hi> who carried a cloth. The L. of <hi>Pluuault</hi> and <hi>Brangerie,</hi> al Officers in our army. More there were whom I cannot well call to minde: but my maſters, thoſe were braue Gentlemen, thoſe were the kings good ſeruants: theſe were the good pillers of our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, whom we haue loſt in this battel, whoſe death doeth alſo make our liues
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7932:7"/>ſo wretched, that vndoubtedly they are happier than we that breath foorch this aire that is infectes with our miſeries. I thinke that they whom this loſſe doth moſt concern, ſhuld alſo be moſt fouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the griefe that they ought to conceaue therof: and your ſelues doe I accoumpt ſo affectionate to the benefit of your country that for your partes you will powre forth a whole riuer of teares which will not bee dried vp a great while, conſidering that the loſſe which you receiue doe ſtretch ſo farre, and ſpreadeth farther than the moſt paſſionate can well imagine. Wee doe well know what aſſurance we had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, that all ſhould haue ſuccéeded o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to vs then it hath done, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee are to bee the more ſory becauſe we were deceiued. And albeit Gods will was apparant therein, alſo that it were our partes rather to yeeld thereto than to murmure againſt it, yet can I not but feele that ſuch was the pleaſure of God, to the end ſharply to puniſh vs for repoſing more truſt in our fleſhly arme then in his inightie power, yea and which is more, becauſe wée haue
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7932:7"/>fought and neuer aſked counſell at the mouth of the Lord. Would you haue any more notable teſtimonies to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme my ſaying, then the death of this braue nobilitie? The ſame is but too ſufficient to wreſt from you this belief: and if you doo but beholde the reſt that remaineth captiue with the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> you ſhal as a man would ſay ſée our ſorrow more liuely, as if their captiuitie ſhould vnchaine thoſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes which come in poſte to our op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. The moſt notable of them wil I alſo name vnto you. There is the L. of <hi>Bellegarde,</hi> Gouernor of <hi>Xantonge</hi> and <hi>Angoumois,</hi> who was wounded, taken and ſince deceaſed. The L. of S. <hi>Luc,</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Brouages</hi> &amp; of the Iles of <hi>Xantonge</hi> taken. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>Piennes:</hi> The Earle of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoreau</hi> wounded and taken. The L. of <hi>Sanſac</hi> taken. The L. of <hi>Cypierre,</hi> The L. of <hi>Saultray</hi> of the houſe of <hi>Lude.</hi> The L. of <hi>Montigny</hi> Captaine of the kings gate. The L. of <hi>Ville Comblin</hi> Lieutenant to the L. of <hi>Souuray.</hi> The L. of <hi>Caſtle Renaud Guidon</hi> to the L. of <hi>Sanſac.</hi> The L. of <hi>Maumo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7932:8"/>of the light Horſe. The L. of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triere Guidon</hi> to the L. of <hi>Lauerdin.</hi> The L. of <hi>Ould Caſtle.</hi> The L. <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtelu.</hi> The L. of <hi>Lauuerdiere Guidon</hi> to the L. of <hi>Suze.</hi> All theſe were Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains &amp; men of authoritie, &amp; ſo acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged of all, among when I recken not the Captaines of the foolemen, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther many other priuate Gentlemen that had no charge, and are either ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, wounded or ſlaine. As for thoſe that yet liue, it may be ye ſhall hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter haue ſome comfort of them, as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping they may returne into the kings ſeruice: but I do much feare their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the ſpéech of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of <hi>Nauar,</hi> whoſe particular ſeruants they all, or the moſt of them, haue long béen, neither did euer beare armes againſt him, but againſt their willes: ſuch at the leaſt are their ordinary proteſtations, which in effect they haue often confirmed. Yea did they beare but one ſparke of good affection to the ſaid king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> he is ſkilfull inough thereof to kindle a whole flame: ſo ſhall he winne from vs theſe relikes of our ruines, where with to preuaile againſt our ſelues, if not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7932:8"/>againſt vs, yet indirectly for him ſelfe, but not for vs. For you know what a voice is generally giuen out of his wonderfull grace in winning mens minds and quenching the malice of his enemies, in caſe hee can but once come to let them taſte of his courteſie. Yee may belieue that moſt of theſe our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters being ſo much bounde vnto him, will hereafter continue their bonds, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that there be but few amongſt them to whom the curteſies of this Prince may not preſcribe whatſoeuer lawes he lift. In the meane time he ſhall haue his paſſage frée: For as for the L. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall of <hi>Matignon,</hi> how good a ſeruant ſo euer hee be to the king, hee is tied to <hi>Gaſcogne:</hi> and beſides his forces are not ſufficient to ſtop the ſaid king from executing whatſoeuer his purpoſes as eaſily as he would wiſh, neither can he at this day deſire or put in execution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing whatſoeuer with greater ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, hauing obteined ſuch a braue vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory againſt vs, which is perfect in all notable parts. The death and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment of all the chiefe Captaines, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the L. of <hi>Lauerdin</hi> who ſéeing our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7932:9"/>conflict a far off, went to ſaue him ſelfe and few others, the winning of the field, the taking of the artillery, the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our armies lodgings, the chace purſued foure leagues, and a thouſand other particularities which I heere o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. Concerning the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> I haue heard credibly reported that hée was one of the ſharpeſt in fight, &amp; buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led earneſtly, yea ſo farre foorth as by force to cary away <hi>Chaſteau-renauds</hi> Cornet, alſo to haue receiued a taint in the necke with a ſpeare &amp; other blowes that bruiſed his hands and face. To be briefe, that hee ſhewed himſelfe a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in ordering his battailes and a ſouldier in fight. As for the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> that hee fought valiantly &amp; had one horſe killed vnder him, alſo that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing horſed againe he tooke the L. of S. <hi>Luc</hi> priſoner who had before borne him downe. That the Earle of <hi>Soiſons</hi> in this firſt reencounter ſhewed ſo good proofe of his courage that he greatly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented his partakers &amp; gaue them good hope of himſelfe, for he ioyned earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with his owne handes tooke the Marqueſſe of <hi>Piennes</hi> priſoner, ſo as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7932:9"/>theſe thrée Princes fighting with their enemies, fought ſo reciprocally whoſe vertue ſhould beſt appeare, that they haue no cauſe one to enuy an other, ſith they all ſhewed all duetie according as the occurrences miniſtred occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it to be doubted, but theſe ſo aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Captaines did greatly aſſure their members, among whom the L. of <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renne</hi> alſo had his horſe ſlaine in the battell and entered verie farre, as alſo did the L. of <hi>Trimouille</hi> who was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of great courage and aſſurance in the front of his light horſemen. Finally that there was no troope in all their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my but had a ſhare in the glorie of our ouerthrow. Herein haue wee cauſe to be ſory, ſith the hurt that we do to them do but prouoke our men, and that either early or late they will finde meanes to requite vs: howbeit at this time it is much more then a requitall, neither is there any compariſon betwéene all the harme that we haue done them, yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit you ſet togither all that haue hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened ſince the beginning of the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and the ſame which wee haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in this battell. One onelie ſhort
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7932:10"/>day hath recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced all that they haue loſt in two yéeres and a halfe, which is the time ſince the league was reuealed, and as farre as I ſée, wee are yet farre in their debts. We haue ſéene all the mightie armies which the king hath ſent out of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prouinces of the realme to make an ende. But ſhew mee now what fruit hath come of them? The ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of townes? wee haue taken none but ſuch as they made no great account to kéepe, and all but loures which were neuer, as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould ſay, of any name, but through miſhap. And how haue we gotten them? with large time, exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue expences, and a world of labor and pollicie, which heeretofore would not haue béen practiſed at the ſiege of <hi>Metz,</hi> S. <hi>Quintins,</hi> and other good Townes in our daies. What haue we gained? we haue taken nothing by aſſault, and all our ſieges haue ended by profitable and honourable compoſition for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged. Neither haue our ſieges any whit diminiſhed their number, ſith the lawes of warre haue freed them from the fury of our weapons. And which is worſe, <hi>Caſtillon</hi> the Duke of <hi>Mayns</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:7932:10"/>proudeſt trophee, the taking whereof coſt ſixe weekes worke and ſix hundred thouſand francks hath the Lord of <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renne</hi> recouered in one houre, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any expenſe. The king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> hath in leſſe then thrée wéekes taken <hi>Tallemo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, <hi>S.</hi> Meſſan, Fontenay, Mail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lezay, Mauleon,</hi> &amp; fiue or ſixe good Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles more. The ſaid D. of <hi>Ioyeuſe</hi> came to recouer theſe loſſes, but hee ſpent moſt of his time in preparatiues, and in the end at the ſiege of S. <hi>Maiſſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> was driuen to diſcharge <hi>113.</hi> Cannon ſhot, againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which it had not coſt the ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> king two hundreth Harquebuze ſhot: and had it not béene for the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw that the ſaid D. of <hi>Ioyeuſe</hi> gaue to the <hi>Mothe</hi> of his two regiments of Collters and Clounes, togither with the controuerſies among the beſieged, we had not had it ſo ſoone or ſo eaſily. As for <hi>Maillezay</hi> which the ſaid Duke of <hi>Ioyeuſe</hi> alſo tooke, he did rather ſuprize then take it, beſides that the ſmal num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſouldiers therein feared his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. But <hi>Fontenay</hi> was of ouer hard digeſtion, &amp; the Catholike forces gaue place to the Proteſtants, of whom wée
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7932:11"/>made ſo ſmall account. And whereas there died a good number of them, as could not be otherwiſe choſen, ſo if wée peruſe the rowles of our army, we ſhal find, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the rule of ſubſtraction may ſéem ſufficient to finde out our accounts. The ſwoord, the bad weather, pouertie, peſtilence or other diſeaſes haue taken away ſo many that wee haue but fewe left to habandon to the like miſhappes: and the woorſt is, wee neuer ſéeke to ſpare, but rather doo ſéeme to practiſe this deteſtable ſaying: <hi>Let our friends periſh, ſo as our enemies may periſh alſo.</hi> Moreouer, wherein are their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires empaired? Wee haue kept the field, but how? For the moſt part in ſuch ſeaſons as the retraite into the Townes had béene more fit and ſafe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the iniuries of wind and ſnow: in ſuch a ſeaſon I ſay, as albeit they had béene as well able to haue kept the field as we, yet had it béen wiſedome to to habandon it vnto vs, ſo to ſuffer vs to conſume our ſelues, with a million of inconueniences which fought againſt vs, although they meddle not at all. Likewiſe when the time fauoured our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7932:11"/>voyages, beſides that the ſame was but ouer ſhort, we haue found ſuch reſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in them, &amp; they haue giuen vs ſo ſmall hold, that our ſelues haue beaten our ſelues with our owne paines, and haue reaped but the diſhonour of doing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and blame for working too much miſchiefe: and to be briefe, all our fires are in the ende conuerted into ſmoake which hath choked vs. The raiſing vp of our bucklers were haughtie, but when we came to the matter &amp; to take hold, wee brought foorth nothing but confuſion &amp; diſorder, wherein the king of <hi>Nauarres</hi> part hath béene rather vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held then ſhaken, ſo as we ſéeme to bee but the winds which breake vpon their conſtancy or magnanimitie. Twentie yeares ago &amp; more might I haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned how hard a matter it was vtterly to ouerthrow him: but I neuer thought it vnpoſſible vntill theſe our laſt trials, wherein he hath taught vs that hée ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is a greater one then wée, or elſe that he hath more ſupporters then wée haue force: or both. I will not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to confeſſe that at the beginning of theſe troubles our great preparatiues
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7932:12"/>for war againſt him did make me ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly to belieue that hee could haue no means to kéep himſelfe from vs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon my ſelfe as well as many other did according to my duetie bring in whatſoeuer I was able togither with my own perſon: and notwithſtanding all our delaies and the lingering of our purpoſes, yet did I not neuertheles diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire of good ſucceſſe: but now am I forced to pluck my pin from the ſtake, and earneſtly to open mine eies to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the cauſes of our miſfortune, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither with the neceſſitie of a farther cauſe of miſchiefe, wherof this late one is but the firſt, or at the leaſt the moſt apparant beginning. Not my maiſters that I will reſemble thoſe foules which ſo ſoone as colde weather commeth on doe habandon euerie climate, by anie raſh alteration of my wil which ſo long and reſolutely I haue alwaies kept. For I proteſt, that of all the reaſons that may bee imagined in this noueltie I do admit onely the ſame which ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth before me the preſeruation of that eſtate, for the which ſo farre I am from all feare of the loſſe of my firſt pretence,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7932:12"/>that I wiſh rather to loſe my ſelfe: and in the name of God doo exhort you ſo wel to try my aduice, that you may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low therof, and enſuing the ſame, ſhew ſo good an example to the reſt of <hi>Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> that ſith your ſelues are the light that ſhould lighten vs, this eſtate may alſo by your meanes recouer her auncient brightneſſe, and this oppreſſed people perfect reliefe from all their afflictions.</p>
            <p>To enter therefore into the matter, my ſelfe haue alwaies béene through zeale to religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thruſt for ward, &amp; when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer there fell out any ſpéech of the defence thereof, I came as hotely as might be deſired. Now this religion I alwaies held in ſuch ſort as I receiued of my predeceſſors, and as I account it true ſaluation of my ſoule, I preferred it before all other whatſoeuer worldly conſiderations. Wherein I was confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not onely by this domeſticall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, but alſo by that doctrine which your ſelues haue alwaies deliuered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, referring al that poſſibly I might vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authoritie which long you haue obteined and kept among our nation. I will not bee aſhamed to ſay that in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7932:13"/>this caſe I haue willingly repoſed my ſelfe vpon you, as imagining that you would not damme your ſelues in ſport, as alſo that in ſo good company I could not doo amiſſe. In conſideration wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I neuer troubled my ſelfe much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſearch into the depth of theſe miſteries and difficulties wherein your ſchoole is as it were plunged, leauing to you the arguing in words, and reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to my ſelfe the deciſions in action, wherewith as néede required, to yéeld authoritie to your decrées, and for my part ſtoutly to oppoſe my ſelfe againſt all thoſe that woulde withſtand you, howbeit vnder the authoritie of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neraigne magiſtrate, to whom I neuer doubted of my due obedience. Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I alwaies ſuppoſed that our warre was not lawful againſt al ſuch as ſhot againſt you and ſought to ſubuert your doctrine, accounting them verie here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes &amp; Apoſtataes from the Church, with whom we were to ſtriue euen for life, conſidering that their opinions did for the moſt part kill vs, by rauiſhing from vs through their frowardneſſe, that which I ſuppoſed you had impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7932:13"/>vnto vs in ſincere and faithful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences. For this which I haue often heard you ſay, did I take for an infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible principle: that is to ſay, <hi>That our Church can not erre, alſo, that to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe you of error, was ſuch an error as deſerued to be purſued with fire and ſworde.</hi> Thus was I neuer of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other mind, but that we had a moſt firme and more than neceſſarie foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation euery way to perſecute thoſe whom men tearme <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> So preſumpteous a title could not I like of: &amp; as in theſe latter ages, Gods ſpirit threatneth vs with ſundrie ſeducers, ſo haue I alwaies accounted theſe men to be, whereupon I haue deteſted their companies: ſo farre haue I béene from ſparing, whatſoeuer I could poſſibly doe, to vſe againſt them all rigors whereby to roote them out. For this cauſe doe I make great account of the deuotion which diuers of our kinges haue at ſundrie times ſhewed. But ſéeing that the more we ſtriue, the more this people increaſe: the large expert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of theſe affaires maketh mee the more ſtacke in theſe matters, and their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7932:14"/>late victorie which God hath giuen them, cauſeth me to imagine that hee doth wholy fauor their cauſe, alſo that whatſoeuer croſſes hee doth by our hands lay vpon them, hee doth neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe reſerue vnto them a happie &amp; a comfortable end. <hi>Diſorder</hi> (ſaith a certaine auncient) <hi>breedeth good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees,</hi> and <hi>the reiteration of our tranſgreſsions when wee finde them doe worke vs, to our knowledge, wiſedome: yea the apprentiſhip of our owne loſſes is more ſtrong and forceable then that which procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth of others harmes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I doe therefore willingly ſuffer my ſelfe to bee carried away with that whoſe effects doe teach me to procéede further, not that I will ſearch out all the contentious pointes betwene the one and the other: for as yet I haue not taken ſo much paines: but onely in reſpect of the proceedings vſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their perſons and goods. Firſt you are all to debate in matter of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: you differ in ſundrie articles, and yet doe agrée in the ground, which is, <hi>one onely Ieſus, Chriſt mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7932:14"/>God and man, and ſole head of the Chruch.</hi> I pray you, is this a matter to be decided by your murders? is it ſuch a controuerſie as may bee ſo determined? how can you graunt life to his ſoule, whoſe bodely life you haue taken away? how can you ſaue thoſe to whom you graunt no time to belieue? or how would you haue them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue without preaching vnto? Theſe be the ordinarie complaintes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they vſually appeale from our purſutes, which notwithſtanding they ſéeme iuſt, yet doe we ſtop our eares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them as againſt the maremaids ſong. But why doe you denie them all frienndly conference for the deciſion of your controuerſies? I know you will anſwere that it is a matter that hath already beene preferred, and yet hath not profited. But the Lawiers haue taught me, that whatſoeuer hath béene fraudulently done, is accounted as wonne: for in all our aſſemblies our procéedings haue béene vnperfect, for proofe whereof I referre my ſelfe to the acts of the <hi>Councel of Trent,</hi> and late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the <hi>parley at Poyſſy.</hi> Concerning
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7932:15"/>the firſt, there was neuer action more impertinent, then that wherein they were condemned, and yet neither were or could be heard, conſidering that their aduerſaries were alſo their iudges: as alſo your ſelues doe know, that the <hi>French Church</hi> did neuer in all and through all alow of it, witneſſe the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales there againſt made: albeit I ſay nothing of the oppoſition of our kings, whereby this counſaile may not be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted as irreuocable in <hi>Fraunce:</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe we ſhall reueale our partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie in ruling their condemnation after our owne fantaſies, and not according to the nullitie of the iudgement which vndoubtedly is generall, vntill by the reformation of thoſe articles which we allow not, there can bee no fault found therein. For otherwiſe by taking and leauing what wee liſt, wee ſhoulde play too open. Such alſo the like priuiledge groweth of the ſame reaſon, why will you not ſuffer the profeſſors of the pretended reformed religion to enioy the like libertie of iudgement as your ſelues? As for the <hi>parley</hi> at <hi>Poyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy</hi> I remember that the chiefe contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7932:15"/>which concerned the ſacrament of the altar, was in a manner agréed: alſo that looking into our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, wee ſhall finde that our owne partakers vpon a politike diſcretion interrupted it, leſt the ouerthrow of that foundation ſhoulde haue pulled downe the whole building. Euer ſince that time, I imagined that it was well doone to ſticke to antiquitie, but ſince calling to mind that the miniſters plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their cauſe out of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and the auncient Doctors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable thereto, I can not thinke but that, except in reſpect of the time, in caſe they verifie their allegations, they can not be but well grounded, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, that if wee ſpeake but of the opinion of our <hi>Popes</hi> only, who beſides for the moſt part haue not béene the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſteſt men in the world, we ſhall loſe our cauſe outright. But when I doe more nearely conſider of your ſelues, I doe runne into ſome further miſtruſt: for can you that profeſſe the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and teaching of the ſcriptures, want iudgement to comprehend them, or fidelitie to deliuer them? Shall theſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7932:16"/>reformed perſons haue that priuiledge aboue you, to whome it hath béene purchaſed ſo long agoe? Are you lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned like to thoſe high prieſtes mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the holy ſcriptures, among whom Gods law was periſhed? Will God conceale his myſteries from your greatnes, and reueale them to their baſenes? Can you forge vnto your ſelues anie Cabal in lew of the doctrine of Gods ſpirite? Haue the ſubtilties of the ſerpent made you to rebell againſt your creator? I dare not imagine thus much of you, albeit your aduerſaries doe ſufficiently caſt it in your téeth. But I coulde rather wiſh them to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from iniuring of you, and to bee content ſimply to expound their owne ſayings, as alſo that you did the like by them: howbeit you haue growne ſo far into wordes with them, that we haue beene at handiblowes for your ſakes, whereby theſe braules doe ſéeme to bee the more irreconciliable, wherein I ſaid that hetherto we haue taken a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie wrong courſe, in miniſtring a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue to the wound before we tryed ſuch ſuppliant ointments as might perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7932:16"/>haue yéelded ſome eaſe. The miſchiefe was but in bréeding, but we through our haſtie and headlong procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings haue ſodenly brought it to extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie: ſo that in lew of appeaſing theſe troubles of the Church, wee haue alſo brought in the troubles of the Eſtate; as if our peace depended onely vpon confuſion: yea we haue ſo ſhuſled the Cardes, that we can not finde againe the principall. We all haue beene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to grow ſo obſtinate in your obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacies, that for the preſeruing of you, ſome haue hazarded, and others quite loſt them ſelues: for the maintaining of your rents, we haue ſpent our owne: for your amitie, we haue entred enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with our owne kinſmen: vnder the pretence of the honour of God, men haue ſhamefully entreated men: to be briefe, Religion hath cauſed vs in the inſolencies of our warres to treade all religion vnder foote: alſo whereas it had béene more méete and profitable gently to haue reduced thoſe that were ſtrayed, to the folde, wee haue beene their butchers. In lew of ſhewing the way to thoſe that went amiſſe, wee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7932:17"/>haue thruſt them into the mire: in lew of preſenting <hi>Ioſeph</hi> vnto <hi>Iacob,</hi> wee haue ſhewed onely his garment tain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in bloud, whiles him ſelfe mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the pitte: in lew of receyuing the angels with the conuerſion of theſe miſerable perſons, we haue made them ſorrowfull through their deathes, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, God deſireth not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he may bee conuerted and liue. The holy Ghoſt ſpeaketh of the ſpirituall death, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we are the cauſe when we preuent their repentance with their deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. What profit haue you found in giuing vs counſell, euen from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to take arme againſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended reformed? Did you not meane that they ſhould haue béene rooted out and we preſerued? haue yee your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires? Are not you, I pray you, guiltie of the deathes of ſo many as vpon ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie haue followed your counſels? with what conſciences doe you ſtaye vs to kill others: are not you the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners to both parties? ſée you not that in lew of diminiſhing their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you leſſen ours? that wee loſe as
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7932:17"/>many friendes on our owne partes as enimies of theirs? that we can not wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them without weakening of our ſelues? what profit is there in this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitie? They render you blow for blow: aſſault for aſſault: battell for bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell: victorie for victorie: and in the end you are alwaies forced to accept of their conditions of peace: yet is there nothing that can make vs giue ouer. We ſtill play the kites with their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels, which neuertheleſſe doe dayly grow vp againe: we ordinarily draw away their bloud, which neuer dryeth vp: and which is worſe, we ſtill incurre as much loſſe as we procure them, and conſuming our enimies, doe waſt our owne bloud, and yet can not perceiue that you be any whit moued at our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, as if our labours were your reſt, and our ſorrowes your contentation: you laugh when others wéepe, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſe thruſting forward the wheele of theſe calamities, whereby to aſſure your felicitie. But I can not finde that we haue any profit in all this, and I wonder that our long expence which we haue had theſe twentie or twentie
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7932:18"/>and fiue yeares can not inſtruct vs in our leſſon. This is the ſeuenth ciuill warre that wee haue leagued againſt theſe reformed, and yet we are now to beginne. True it is that we haue wun ſome victories, but all is but vanitie: if we haue gotten the field, alas! wee haue ſéene it couered likewiſe with a great part of our owne men: and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into our tents, wee haue heard the mournings at our owne families. At our departure thence, what haue we done but made warre to the end to purchaſe peace? what is become of all our purpoſes to roote out this people whom wee haue found ſo reſolute in their defence? we haue returned thence into our cloſets then with ſhame and miſfortune: then haue we ſodden them againe, but they that haue endeuoured to digeſt them, haue found them to bee but fiſh. And yet are wee ſo farre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched, as among all theſe diſeaſes to thinke that we be in health: ſtill there are ſome firebrands readie to kindle our diſſentions, and they that ſhoulde caſt on water, doe poure on oyle, brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, and pitch, leaſt the fire ſhould goe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7932:18"/>out. When I examine all theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedings, I leaue to the perſecuted, and in my doubt of religion, I doe the more fauor their cauſe becauſe of the onely token of perſecution. Thus haue I learned to iudge by a place that lately I redde in <hi>S. Hierom</hi> heretofore, one of the famous prieſts of the Romiſh Church. <hi>He</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that is purſued, doth imitate Chriſt, but he that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth or perſecuteth is Antichriſt.</hi> Not that I meane to iuſtifie all thoſe heretikes whom our kinges haue ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, as the <hi>Gothes</hi> who were <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> and of late the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> for they were monſters, of whom the firſt ſubuerted the groundes of our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, namely the diuinitie of Ieſus: an intollerable caſe among Chriſtians, and yet the warre that hath béene lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uied againſt them, had other founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions than religion. The <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> beſides their apparant errors in religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did alſo peruert the right of magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and both the one and the other were by one conſent condemned euen in the moſt reformed Churches. As for the <hi>Albigeois</hi> following ſuch ancient
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7932:19"/>recordes as I haue found contrarie to the writings of our Hiſtoriographers, I feare they were oppreſſed rather vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſtomacke then equitie. But I wil leaue thoſe paſſed examples and come onely to the reaſon of things preſent. I could well like to haue our Church purged from hereſies and heretikes: but I muſt withall miſtike the pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it with our owne bloud: neither can I thinke theſe ſo violent meanes to be either lawfull or ſufficient. Ieſus Chriſt tooke a whippe to driue the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney chaungers out of the temple, but wee are farre inough from doing the like. For thoſe men did not falſifie the Law, or the Prophets: but verie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly, they made the houſe of God which was ordained onely for prayer, their market place. They did abuſe the holy place, with profane trafike, and ſo conſequently this puniſhment of Ieſus Chriſt was but politike. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that in the meane time he was ordinarily conuerſant among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſts, Scribes, and Phariſies, entring and diſputing in their Sinagogues, and yet neuer laying hand vpon them, albeit
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:7932:19"/>they were the verie falſifiers of the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophecies of his own coming. Our ſauior Chriſts kingdom is not of this world: the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon wherewith he fighteth with his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies, are ſpirituall: neither is his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation purchaſed by mans arme: how much more neceſſarie then were it to defend religion by the true vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the ſcriptures, by reformation of our liues, by prayers and holy deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the ſeruice of God, by teaching the ignorant, ſetting reaſons againſt opinions, and antiquitie againſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueltie: and to be briefe, by hearkening to the voice of our ſhepeheard, in lew of thoſe who to the end to bewitch vs with their dreames doe ſhroude them ſelues vnder that title? This is the cauſe, why from henceforth I doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to depart from theſe cruelties which are but too ordinarie among vs, and to begge pardon of the God of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, whom I beſéech with the truth of his word to ſhine into the bottomleſſe gulſes of my ignorance, to the end that leaning no longer to the outward ſhew of men, I may behold the righteouſnes
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7932:20"/>of this cauſe, for the which theſe poore reformed perſons doe ſo long and ſo conſtantly abide whatſoeuer the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to them afforde: notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all our torments, they ſhake not, and that is it that ſhaketh me, yea and I wonder that the loſſe of their goods, maketh them not to abandon their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Their benefit muſt be verie great, ſith ſo many calamities can not make them to giue it ouer: and we may well ſay, that they haue a verie bright and large knowledge, in that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding whatſoeuer hope of domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call eaſe we propound, they can neuer miſtake. I ſée them lurke in euerie place, depriued of their rents, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeged with a thouſand neceſſities, and yet can neuer be baniſhed their aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies and patient bearing of their opreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. Surely they are not ſo ſenſeleſſe as vpon pleaſure to ſuffer ſo many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences, ſo that of neceſſitie they muſt bee inuited and ſtrengthened by ſome ſtronger matter then the frailtie of this world. Willingly could I ioine with <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> and ſay, <hi>That if this reformed religion be of God, it is in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7932:20"/>vaine for man to labour to deſtroy it, if it be not of him, it will vaniſh of it ſelfe.</hi> Howbeit, I ſéeke not to take the ſword from the magiſtrate, but gladly I would beat iudgement into his head, wherby he might diſcerne the bonds of his duetie: for it is not inough to doe a mans duetie, but he muſt doe it conueniently, according to the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of time, place and perſons which are the ordinarie rules of our actions. <hi>Extreame law is extreame iniurie,</hi> ſay the lawers, and that vpon good reaſon. Nothing can be more iuſt then to puniſh the rebels of a common wealth, as men guiltie of treaſon: but it may ſo happen that this iuſtice may be pernitious, and as a man may ſay, vniuſt. If the whole bodie of a towne or prouince ſhoulde riſe againſt their Soueraigne, yet if they ſhould fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into his hands, he ought to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the conſeruation of ſo many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons before their deſtruction, becauſe of the great benefit that would enſue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, namely the preſeruation of one portion of his realme, as lately did the L. Conſtable at <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> and the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:7932:21"/>Senate</hi> many times with the peoples mutinies: whereas contrarie wiſe the violences of <hi>Silla</hi> and <hi>Marius</hi> who put their fellow citizens euen by thouſands to the ſword, were deteſtable and almoſt vnworthie to be ſpoken off. When the miſchiefe is ſo great as it can not be cured without euident dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, it is better to tollerate it in the weake parte, than to loſe all: as it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth to thoſe, of whom when the palſie hath taken hold of halfe the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, no wiſe phiſition will counſell to diuide it from the other halfe that is yet in health. Now if this conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may take place in all diſeaſes ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, much more then in ſuch as are of long continuance, and lightly more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable then the later: euen ſo then when one parte of a ſtate is by what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer meanes deuided from the other, wee muſt bee verie warie of making them to méete, eſpecially when ſuch means bringeth now vtter confuſion to the whole bodie, and that the infected partes be noble and eſſentiall: for in a miſchiefe, in a maner vniuerſall, tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in it ſelfe is farre more neceſſary
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:7932:21"/>then the triall of the vtter rooting of it out when it paſſeth our ſtrength, &amp; that there is ſo great equalitie that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat ought ſtill to be in doubt. And ſuch are thoſe which we terme neceſſarie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, which beeing preſerued, doe alſo preſerue the ſubiect whereto they are adioyned, and ought as a man ſhould ſay, to be more curiouſly entreated then health it ſelfe. Howbeit this ſimilitude may in one reſpect be maimed: for ſuch an inconuenience may grow in a ſtate, that it will be moſt neceſſarie to oppoſe the whole for the whole, and not before trial of the gentle &amp; moſt louing means. And in a monarchie wee muſt aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the crown and ſcepter againſt him that aduentureth wrongfully to take it away. And why? becauſe that euerie defenſiue warre is moſt lawfull, and eſpecially when your whole ſtate is called into queſtion. Yea, which is more, you are by nature bound therto, and in caſe you bee retchleſſe therein, you do inwardly betraie your country. The like is it in all matters wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dependeth your authoritie, togither with the preſeruation of your rightes,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:7932:22"/>which ought to be inuiolable. It is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the duetie of euerie ſoueraigne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate diligently to watch, and vpon neceſſitie ſtoutly to employ himſelfe. But ſo long as the ſtate is not touched, there can be no cauſe ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſet the Monarke againſt his ſubiects, ſo farre muſt hee be from ſhrowding himſelfe with the vaile of religion to oppreſſe his realme, notwithſtanding whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the diuerſities thereof, eſpecially if the number of the contrarie partie bée innumerable, alſo that tolleration may be a manifeſt occaſion of reſt. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore albeit theſe pretended reformed, were the moſt damnable heretikes in the worlde, yet conſidering the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of them, the good Townes, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the good prouinces which they enioy, with the mightie &amp; valiant Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines that ſupport them, it were but in vaine for vs to enterpriſe to aſſaile them, from who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we can bring nothing but the tokens of their ſtomackes, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding whatſoeuer forrain ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour we haue had to ſupport vs, &amp; that they haue hitherto reſiſted vs with the faction onely that they haue in <hi>France.</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:7932:22"/>So far ſhall we be from doing them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie harme at all, if they get their forren helpe. Beſides this, we cannot well caſt them off from amongſt vs without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme inhumanitie: for, for the moſt part they be conioyned vnto vs by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinitie, and all generally by like participation of one ſelfe countrie. Far are we from conforming our ſelues to the Iſraelites, who by a certaine iuſt permiſſion of God ſuffered the Iebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites to dwell in <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> albeit the proportion betwéene vs and the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, were without compariſon grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then betwéene them: either to the great Emperor <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> who as witneſſe <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and <hi>Tertullian,</hi> Doctors of the Church and men woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie credite, during his Empire tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an hundred ſectes, but eſpecially the <hi>Arrians,</hi> whom thrée or foure Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors before him had fauoured, who wer founded both by preſcription of time, and by eight Councels which had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed their hereſie after the ſame of <hi>Nice,</hi> and namely the Councell of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini,</hi> where ſixtie Biſhops maintei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Arrianiſme,</hi> &amp; onelie thrée perſons
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:7932:23"/>ſtucke to the trueth: and yet <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> himſelfe perſeuered conſtantly in true religion, wherin he cauſed his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to bee inſtructed, and ſo did more weaken <hi>Arrianiſme</hi> then hee coulde haue done by anie violence of decrées, which he ſurceaſed. I will not bring in for example the Turke, who tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all kindes of religion, for that I minde to kéepe the Chriſtians within Chriſtendome, but ſurely he doeth the more ſtedfaſtly eſtabliſh his eſtate, for that men being glad of libertie, care not for troubling his eſtate that graunteth them peace. Behold <hi>Germany</hi> &amp; <hi>Pole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> you ſhal ſée no nation ſo diuers in religion as they, and yet can they ioyne in a common peace, neither doo the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of opinions diuide their eſtates. As for the Catholike king, he at the firſt eſtabliſhed his Inquiſition ſo ſurelie that theſe reformed haue had no great opportunitie to ſettle themſelues in <hi>Spaine,</hi> but for the low Countries hée cannot yet compaſſe it there, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doundeth to the great detriment &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of his affaires, how good a face ſoeuer hée ſet vpon the matter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:7932:23"/>
But God hath giuen him that bone to gnaw vpon, leaſt he ſhould imploy his great wealth to the deſtruction of any his mightie neighbor, which with the incredible treaſure that this Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh warre hath waſted, he might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture haue done: yet doe I not thinke but euerie of you doe abhorre the infinite miſchiefes which his obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie hath bred: for through the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall loue that is rooted in vs, we iudge more fréely of others then of our ſelues: and in déede wee haue taken pittie of them: witneſſe the French troupes at ſundrie times led thither, and euen late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſame which the late <hi>Monſieur</hi> brought, albeit the whole haue had but had ſucceſſe, either for our honors or the profite of thoſe poore tirannized peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Howbeit, we haue alwaies in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parance ſhewed what griefe wee haue conceyued of their deſolation: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore notwithſtanding whatſoeuer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie of religion the <hi>Catholike French</hi> could runne to their ſuccour, albeit we haue conuerted our furie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſame faction among vs: ſo diuers haue wee beene to helpe ſome,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:7932:24"/>and to oppreſſe other ſome, euen thoſe to whom we were more bound to ſhew fauour and curteſie. Neuertheleſſe I will not ſay, that the <hi>Catholikes</hi> tended chiefely to aide the reformed in <hi>Flanders,</hi> ſimply in reſpect of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: but I pretend thereby onely to ſhew that they haue all great reaſon to maintain their felow countrimen, who ſhroud them ſelues vnder the ſame cloake of reformation, as to ſuccour ſtrangers. Concerning theſe men, they propound to them ſelues charitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes their neighbors, and hatred of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> with the deſire of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: neither haue wee feared to make the <hi>Catholikes</hi> protectors of the <hi>Reformed</hi> againſt the <hi>Catholikes,</hi> and yet doo we make a conſcience to vſe the like curteſie to ours againſt our ſelues, which wee might with much more eaſe, profit and commoditie, doe: conſidering that thereof doe depend the preſeruation &amp; eminencie of the eſtate.</p>
            <p>Thus much haue I thought good now to ſay vnto you concerning this matter, beſéeching you, my maiſters, to examine my reaſons, &amp; thereto to adde
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:7932:24"/>ſuche as your diſcretions are able to performe, whereby wee all may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the reſtoring of our affaires. In the name of God doe I exhort you to enter into ſo déepe conſideration of our miſeries, and the difficultie or rather impoſſibilitie of our purpoſes, that we may ſhortly after manie ſtormes taſte of ſome tranquillitie, bearing faithfull counſels to the king in this matter, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as by the duetie of your func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions you are bound. The kingdome of Chriſt is deſtinate to troubles: true: but woe vnto thoſe that are the cauſers thereof. This ſacred ſhepeheards ſhéepe ought not to become wolues: or they to whom Chriſt hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded peace, to make warres: or Gods children to murder their bretheren.</p>
            <p>But I ſpeake only to you my mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, whom I acknowledge to bee the principall court which at this day doe miniſter whatſoeuer motion you liſt to our affaires: conſider that it is your parts to become mediators in all theſe funerall diuiſions: to reunite, if not in religion, yet at the leaſt in peace al theſe partakers, which are ſo fleſhed one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:7932:25"/>an other. Hitherto haue you béen content to caſt your torches betwéene our armies, and ſodenly after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the auncient Prieſts of <hi>Rome,</hi> to retire into place of ſafetie. Now is it time for you to run and quench them: otherwiſe you ſhall daily loſe your great ſupporters, and in the ende grow ſo weake, that they whom you thinke weakeſt ſhall ouer rule you: your force dependeth onely vpon peace, whereas in the warres, beſides that theſe refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med doe catch from the Clergie infinite treaſures, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe that are left do va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh with the aire, &amp; ſéem only to fatten vp ſuch as vnder colour of fauouring of you, doe but ſéeke to get their liuings. Many of our Popes haue agreed our kings with the Emperors and Engliſh men, when we had but forren warres: greater reaſon then haue you in theſe ciuill and domeſticall diſſentions, the moſt intollerable or odious in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, to ſéeke ſome way ſo to do. Whoſoeuer ſhall ſay to his brother, <hi>Racha,</hi> is by God himſelfe accurſed, what then ſhall you hee, if not onelie in wordes, but in déede alſo you build the diſſipation of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:7932:25"/>your neighbours? And what clemency can you looke for of God that are ſo cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell to men? ſo cruell I ſay euen to your ſelues? I will ſpeake boldly vnto you my maiſters. I feare if you long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue this ſauage life, it will happen to you as it did to <hi>Eſau,</hi> that for want of being in Gods houſe, you wil looſe your birthright. For ſo long as you purſue theſe reformed, you are as it were in the wilderneſſe, where you runne thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting after their blood, and the whiles haue no care to ſerue your heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. So as vnleſſe I bee deceiued, at your returne the gate of his mercy wil bee ſhutte againſt you: you ſhall bee knowne, but not acknowledged to bee his children: and finally theſe cruelties will inherite crueltie, theſe oppreſſions oppreſſion, and theſe iniquities ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. Beware my maiſters, for albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it you deceiue men, God ſeeth your hearts, and to him all ſecrets are open: ſuffer not religion to be the belweather vnto the ſubuerters of this ſtate, and as the ſhorteſt follies are the beſt, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent your ſelues that you haue brought things into that diſpaire wherein wée
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:7932:26"/>now ſée them, and ſo long as there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny likelihood of recouerie, delate not your abilitie anie longer, leaſt it fléete away in the violence of our miſhaps. As for the league whereto you haue lent the vizard of religion, conſider that you cheriſh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſerpent that killeth you: you haue ſwallowed henbane which maketh you to die without féeling. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member you not that when it was firſt reuealed, you were not named? as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déed what religion could they think on that purpóſed onelie impietie? Could they that ſhot onelie at your kings per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon your head &amp; protector, and his ſtate to order it after their fantaſies, call you to warrant their religion? you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhould preach nothing but obedience to the magiſtrate? Hereunto doo the blind ſée as clerely as the daie. Theſe ſhameleſſe perſons thought vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing leſſe then religion: The death of the Lords an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, the ſpoile of his crown did they leuell at: witnes their practiſes againſt the beſt and moſt Catholike Townes in <hi>France,</hi> for they neuer medled with the reformed or attempted againſt anie thing to them apperteining. And I
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:7932:26"/>maruaile how beeing ſo fierce againſt theſe partakers of common quiet, as ye were at the beginning you can now be ſo drunke with their hipocriſie as yee are, albeit you ſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but for a vailet and to ſay truth, you haue but the fooles part in the tragedie that they plaie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Theater of <hi>France.</hi> What pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection néeded you when no man ſeemed to moleſt you? who gaue them this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice ouer your ſoueraigne? néeded he to be conſtrained to your defence, which hee euer ſo willingly tooke vpon him? could not you be defended but by war? had you not for certaine yéeres tried the defence of peace? was it not poſſible to liue in ſo faire a path without murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all the world? All <hi>France</hi> before the laſt troubles did wee ſée in ſo good peace that the controuerſies in religion did nothing impeach the concord of one or other: trafick was growne common againe, the waies were frée through all parts of the realme, what loſſe had you by it: wherin were you troubled? who moleſted you, either in your goods or perſons? Enioyed you not your church rents euen among theſe reformed? did
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:7932:27"/>you not eate and drinke togither with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out outrage? who euer complained of this contentation? As for theſe refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, which of them during this time refuſed the obedience that the ſubiect oweth to his Prince? who haue defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him of his roiall prerogatiues? what taxes or ordinarie Subſidies haue they reiected? who amongſt them followed not the ordinarie courſe of iuſtice? who conſpired againſt the ſtate? your ſelues my maiſters will confeſſe there was no fault in them. If by obſeruing their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion they did amiſſe, it was by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the king and all the ſoueraigne Courtes of this realme: by the conſent, I ſaie, ſo ſolemnely ſworne: the infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging whereof ſéemeth to mende their cauſe: not that I will laie the blame vpon the king: but onelie vpon thoſe whoſe violence haue brought him to this extremitie, to falſefie his word for the breaking of their pernitious drifts, and to turne to theſe rebels, ſo to turne the ſtorme that they had moued againſt him into the innocencie of theſe peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able perſons. Thus doe ſuch as are in danger of ſhipwracke, abandon their
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:7932:27"/>owne goods to relieue their veſſell, albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it this forced will be a will, ſith the firſt motions reſt in him that executeth it. But I will enter no farther into the conſiderations which the king may haue had to gainſay himſelfe, and yet will I boldly ſay, that hee neuer did thing ſo preiuditiall to his ſtate, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he hath moſt euident proofes, and I beſéech God to bee content with that is paſt, and to withdraw his hand from of his people, and grant vs ſome releaſe from theſe oppreſſions. As alſo your ſelues doe in déede know, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the purſuit of the Penſioners of the leagued remaining about his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, what adoo there was to make his maieſtie reſolue himſelfe thereto. This his cléere iudgement perceiued the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious conſequence of aſſotiation, but hee wanted ſupporters to vphold him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, conſidering that the chiefe Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of his counſell, who before had bound their faith to theſe Princes, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer deſiſted from bending of him that way, neither haue I alwaies béene of that minde, but did long perſuade my ſelf that the ſtedfaſtneſſe of our affaires
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:7932:28"/>conſiſted in this inconſtancie, howbeit I was forced to bee as it were ſheitle witted, and by diuorcement from vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to marry with reaſon. For ſith the king knew well inough that there was no quarell but at his eſtate, hee ſhould haue made no difficultie to call about him ſuch as haue moſt intereſt therein, as the Princes of the blood and their power, at the leaſt vpon extremitie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their own offers. That was the way to haue ſuppreſſed the inſolent proceedings of theſe partakers, who fiſh only in puddle water, and vſe our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions to their own eſtabliſhment. For the people would eaſily haue belieued that in truth there was no quarrell but at the ſtate, if the king had vnderprop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped himſelf with the pillers of the ſtate and not béene beaten downe with the winde of religion, albeit ſome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his blood do profeſſe no other then himſelfe: alſo that they which profeſſe anie other, are ſo affectionate to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and the ſeruice of his crowne, that they would not haue béene anie whit more ſlacke in effect then in will. Had there not béen more apparance that hée
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:7932:28"/>ſhould haue ioined with theſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the leaguers? that is, with his friends then with his enemies? with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> French then with the Lorrains? with his own blood then with theſe baſtardes? with the true Officers of his Crowne, then with thoſe that haue béen ſo vndutifull to him? The Romans alwaies appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their domeſticall quarrels, to agrée againſt thoſe that aſſailed them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Gaules,</hi> the <hi>Thuſcans,</hi> or the <hi>Carthaginians.</hi> The like did the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, when the late king <hi>Frances</hi> the firſt, during their reuolt from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Charles</hi> the fift gat from them the realme of <hi>Nauarre.</hi> The diſcent of the Engliſh at <hi>Newhauen, 1562.</hi> bred the reunion of the Frenchmen, ſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne them away: and when wée haue ſéene theſe monſters of <hi>Lorrain</hi> waſte our country, muſt we néeds ioyne with them to help to deſtroy our ſelues? what is become of that auncient French ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue that was woont to goe to fight with the enemy at his owne doore, where now we call him in, wee nouriſh him, we flatter him, and the more harme hée dooth vs, the more we binde our ſelues
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:7932:29"/>to him? This nation which heretofore hath triumphed ouer the Emperours, the <hi>Solimans,</hi> the <hi>Saraſins,</hi> the <hi>Gothes,</hi> and the <hi>Normans,</hi> hath not now béene able to withſtand a handfull of <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards,</hi> and this ſcepter exalted ouer a million of trophees, ſtoopeth to theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, yea they haue almoſt trod it vnder foote. All the honor of valiancy and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage which our predeceſſors haue in twelue hundreth yeares atchieued and kept, haue wee wretchedly loſt in one houre, and theſe Lions that feared no bulles, are now terrefied only with the crowing of a Cocke? Our eſtate doo I now compare to the Rocke mentioned by <hi>Pliny,</hi> which if ye thruſt with your whole bodie neuer ſhaketh, but when you touch it onely with one finger, or rather to that ſtone which being whole fléeteth vpon the water, but broken ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. The whole world, as a man ſhuld ſay, was not able to make <hi>France</hi> to ſhake, and now theſe Muſhromes doe quite ouerthrow it. We altogither haue fléeted vpon the floodes of infinit forrein warres, yet our diuiſions doo drowne vs. This miſerable realme ſéemeth to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:7932:29"/>be growne to her laſt periode, and as that auncient Aſtrologer by the noyſe weules that did gnaw the poſts, iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the houſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was, ſo many wee boldly ſay, that ſith theſe vermine ſtill conſumeth vs, our fall is at hand. What then? muſt the French men become ſtrangers one to an other? can we finde any ſoules ſo diſloiall as to abandon the true ſtock of S. <hi>Lewes,</hi> to embrace theſe wrongfull vſurpers of their right? Thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue béen our true and lawfull Lordes theſe thrée hundreth and ſixtie yeares, (for ſo long is it ſince the raigne of S. <hi>Lewes</hi> head of that race, who alſo gathereth his diſcent from <hi>Merouee</hi>) to thoſe whom we haue not knowne theſe fiftie yeares? ſhall we carry vpon our Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets &amp; ſhoulders, thoſe whoſe vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe and vniuſtice ſhould make to cleane to the earth? ſhall wee plucke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way theſe braue branches of the Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erdeluce which yet remaine, to graft in their places theſe wildings, who as they haue begun, will yéeld foorth nothing but thornes? Oh, who can wiſh this horrible chaunge? This onelie reaſon
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:7932:30"/>might mooue vs to deteſt the ambition of theſe buſie bodies: they aſpire to the Crowne, but they cannot haue it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out murther, and the death of a million of men: thoſe that vphold it, are like to be the firſt that muſt ſtoope: and they that imagine by their meanes to get preferment, ſhall haue peraduenture no other recompence then the loſſe of their liues. To be briefe, for the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of their ambition, we muſt heape vp our tombes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> carkaſes: the heapes of their oppreſſed partakers are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtaies whereby they climbe vp to heauen. Ought wee not to abhorre theſe cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? to ſpit in the faces of theſe ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe perſons that bereaue vs of our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie? To honor thoſe that may peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably and without diſorder aſcend vnto the type of that authoritie which the lawes of the realme &amp; their deſert haue purchaſed for them? Let vs hardlie touch the chiefe ſtring of this game, and ſith theſe men are not aſhamed to doe, let not vs be aſhamed to ſpeake. The <hi>Guizardes</hi> would, to the preiudice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of <hi>Burbon,</hi> inuade this realme, euerie man knoweth it, neither is there
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:7932:30"/>any thing ſo common in the peoples mouthes: wherefore, becauſe the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> who is the néereſt and the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> doo profeſſe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed religion, and ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently are are heretikes. I am ſory that I am no great Doctor, that I might finde out this point of hereſie which ſo oft is caſt in their téeth: but in my mind the chief diſputations of theſe reformed, doo tend only to make the ſimple word of God of more force then mens traditions. That is it whereto they call vs, and I belieue they haue great reaſon, neither that wee are ſo ſufficiently ſhrowded vnder the cloake of the Church, as to thinke that the beautifull title can in effect ſtop all errors: neither is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing ſo eaſie to corrupt as the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of religion, whereof I report my ſelfe to <hi>Noa hes</hi> family, which was ſo holily inſtructed, and yet whence grew all the Idolatrie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> and conſequently of all the reſt of the worlde, except thoſe whom God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued for his people? yea I referre my ſelfe to the ſame people: was there euer thing ſo fraile as thoſe wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches?
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:7932:31"/>whence then came the foure hundreth falſe Prophets againſt one onely <hi>Micheas?</hi> the worſhipping in the high places, and the abhominable ſuperſtitions wherein theſe libertines did ouerflow? neither was it euer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, but that the trueth vpon the beginning of the light thereof, hath had the darkneſſe of lying oppoſite thereto: yea, if I durſt be ſo bolde, as to paſſe common ſpéech, it is the trueth that of neceſſitie bringeth forth lyes, euen as light bringeth forth a ſhadow. For this cauſe, ſo ſoone as Jeſus Chriſt reuealed him ſelfe to be the ſonne of God, al men accounted him a blaſphemer, and the whole courſe of his life ſéemed to thoſe blinde people but a merrie enterlude: ſo ſoone as the Apoſtles had preached the pure doctrine, the diuel ſowed his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purities: yea no man driue them more out of the Church, then they that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them ſelues the Church. <hi>Simon</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magitian oppoſed himſelfe againſt <hi>S. Peter: Cerinthus</hi> againſt <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> and ſo conſequently ſundrie heretikes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Church, as <hi>Ebion, Baſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Marcion, Montanus, Carparates
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:7932:31"/>Sabellicus</hi> and many other, who all for the moſt part endeuored to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the ground of our ſaluation, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: neither hath the Church wanted exerciſe onely againſt her eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but alſo ſhe hath, as I find, béene often moleſted by her owne houſehold ſeruants: <hi>Nouatian</hi> the Prieſt, deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to receyue, ſuch as had reuolted, to penauce: and ſo with the helpe of <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus</hi> a Prieſt of <hi>Carthage,</hi> cauſed a great ſchiſme in the Church. <hi>Samoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus,</hi> being Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed the errors of the <hi>Ebionites. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> a Prieſt of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> had the aſſiſtance of many Biſhops and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, yea, and ſince of whole nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in his hereſie. Now if in theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings, the treaſons of ſuch as ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſerue God were ſo great, there is no doubt but this miſchiefe hath ſtill ſlipped in and béene maintained in the Church. Yea if you can well thinke vpon it, it may bee you will not iudge your ſelues cleane exempt from all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions: but I will ſay no more for feare of incurring your cenſures. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I am ſory you neuer proue the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:7932:32"/>of the proceſſe which the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med haue entred againſt you, and haue long hung vpon the file, alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we muſt belieue ſome rather then other ſome w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any further notice of the matter: for ſo ſhould we be no longer troubled to know whether theſe two princes be heretikes or not. Howbeit admit they be (which hardly and without preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to their replication I can belieue) is it your partes to ſhrinke from their obedience? So did neuer any Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the Primitiue Church againſt the heathen Emperors, to whom in all publike gouernment they ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them ſelues, albeit there could bee no greater difference in religion than was betweene them. Did they reuolt againſt <hi>Conſtantin</hi> the great, who in the end fauoured <hi>Arrius?</hi> againſt <hi>Lici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius?</hi> againſt <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtata:</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Valentinian</hi> and many others that exerciſed tyranny againſt their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion? But the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> is farre from dealing ſo with vs: for he is not yet come to that which wee feare. Thus we cry without a cauſe before we be beaten: not that foreſight is not
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:7932:32"/>an effect of wiſedom, but becauſe it is in vaine to preuent that which wee neither can nor ought to eſchewe. Howſoeuer God giueth vs our kings we muſt ſuffer it: neither is there anie law or lawfull example in the world, that teacheth vs to doe otherwiſe. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the reformed may ſéeme to beare themſelues but badly, in that they take armes againſt their ſoueraigne, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their religion. But beſides that they are iuſtly grounded vpon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue vnder the magiſtrats authority: alſo that nothing is more naturall then to expulſe violence, they doe beſides al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the peremptorie reaſons which often enough they haue giuen vs to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand of, neither is their any fault but in our negligence that wee are not ſufficiently enſtructed thereof. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, the king of <hi>Nauarres</hi> and the P. of <hi>Condes</hi> maner of dealing with our <hi>Catholikes,</hi> might make you to hope of all good entreatie, whenſoeuer things may come to that paſſe. Truely the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> hath alwaies tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Catholike religion in his Realme, which is the lawer <hi>Nauarre,</hi> that is to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:7932:33"/>ſay, a portion of all <hi>Nauarre,</hi> the reſt thereof lying beyond the <hi>Pirinean</hi> mountaines, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> vniuſtly detaine from him. And this can my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe teſtifie, as hauing ſéene it with my owne eyes: for vpon a certaine curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie I trauailed thither two yeares ſince, euen to know whether that which I had heard to the contrarie, were true or no. True it is, that matters are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ordered in his ſoueraignetie of <hi>Bearne:</hi> which is, becauſe at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming thereto, he ſo found them: yea &amp; ſo well eſtabliſhed for the ſpace of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine yeares during the life of his late mother the Quéene of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> that it were very hard, yea vnpoſſible to make any alteration, which alſo is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous vnleſſe any greater benefit be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie apparant. Secondly, his houſe is full of <hi>Catholike</hi> gentlemen which ſerue him, euen in his moſt priuate and notable offices, neither did hee euer make anie difficultie with great cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie to receyue all thoſe that offered them ſelues. This is no token that he will otherwiſe deale whenſoeuer hee ſhall obtaine our eſtate, neither will I
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:7932:33"/>vſe any more then one reaſon gathered of the likelihood, yea, vnleſſe I be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, of the verie trueth. It is not likely that this Prince ſéeing himſelfe exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto the throne, would after ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny troubles, ſéeke other then peace, ſo farre would he be from taking occaſion of warre with his ſubiects, whoſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections he had rather captiuate, then eſtrange: whereupon he will alwaies like that his ſubiects ſhould maintaine their accuſtomed religion, prouided, that the inſolencie of theſe harebraines who ſéeke but to trouble the water, and then to blame the lambes, leaſt they ſhould faile of ſome pretence to deuoure them, doe permit him the like. He may alwaies conſider that the <hi>Catholikes</hi> parte is well vnderpropped: that if his were inuincible, ſo is the other, and therefore that hee ſhall haue a better hand by maintaining of it, then by drawing vpon his eſtate the curſſe of the people, and vpon his conſcience the deſtruction thereof: as alſo I will adde the other of his houſe being <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes,</hi> hauing ſo good part therein, hee will be the more careful for their ſakes. But what? we doe, according to the prouerbe, ſtriue for the <hi>Biſhops cope,</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:7932:34"/>and to no purpoſe doe deuide the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of the liuing, who peraduenture may outline all thoſe that diſpute of thinges to come after his death: yea it ſéemeth, we ſhare out the webbe of his life at our pleaſures: but albeit it bee not lawfull to moue this queſtion, yet may we reſolue it, to the end to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all doubts from thoſe that bréeds preiudice to peace and the common wealth. And indéede, it is as much as to complaine of eaſe. Well you ſée that the king of <hi>Nauars troupes</hi> doe at this day conſiſt as well of the one as of the other ſorte, likewiſe that concord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth amongſt them, whereas the beſt of their profeſſion that cometh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs muſt bee impriſoned &amp; ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomed from all his goodes, yea and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſuffer that death which hee hath not deſerued. Theſe be monſters, they muſt be choaked vp: and many times for the ſatiſfying of the rage of the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the State, we are forced to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie our owne ſelues. I know that the moſt malicious among them doe vſe to gird at this the king of <hi>Nauarres</hi> facilitie, as if the ſame were the baites wherewith he ſéeketh to draw vs into his nettes: but no man can doe ſo wel
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:7932:34"/>as to pleaſe all men: ſtill there is ſome thing to be miſliked, and mens fanſies muſt be tormented for their pleaſures. How would it haue béene, if in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnig abandoning his owne religion for our pleaſures, he had taken ours? Then would they haue ſaid it had béen to curry fauor with vs: that he ſo coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited to the end to deceiue vs: that outwardly hee had beene a <hi>Catholike,</hi> and inwardly reformed in his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: that he had not caſt his olde ſkin: that yet he ſmelt of the faggot: that we muſt waite for his perſeuerance, ſo to know whether he were to bee truſted: In ſumme, the poore Prince had beene wide in his account. And in truth, that had béene the onely way, to haue vnhorſed him outright: for the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med would not haue truſted him, but would haue plaied their partes alone: and the <hi>Catholikes</hi> woulde not at the firſt blow haue committed them ſelues to him, no peraduenture not at all. Yea if the Captaines of the league were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their ghoſtly father, they would ſay they ſhould haue béene verie ſorie if they thought that the <hi>Catholikes</hi> would take his part: and I am ſure they would ſoone labour to be of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:7932:35"/>ſide as heretofore they haue done, ſo to lay a foundation for their ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But ſurely thereby the king of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre</hi> could haue reaped neither honor nor profit: and therefore I doe not thinke it had béene any good counſaile for him ſo to haue done, leaſt he might by that means haue loſt thoſe of whom he is alreadie aſſured: neither can it be any let to any that affect onely the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the ſtate to ioine with him, as of late did the Earle of <hi>Soiſſons.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in as much as which way ſo euer he turne him, the preſent ſtate of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires will ſtill furniſh him of enimies, it wil better beſéeme him to cleaue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to that wherein from his infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie he hath béene brought vp, then light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to intrude him ſelfe into pernicious and vncertaine nouelties. Moreouer, the leſſer is neuer to preſcribe lawe to the ſuperior, and except the kings per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (whom I ſpeeke not of) it is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reaſon that all <hi>Frenchmen</hi> ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to conforme themſelues to the K. of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> then he to ſtoupe to their diſcretion, and bend to their violences: as alſo his dignitie and courage can not digeſt ſuch reproches as they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him, or rigor as they vſe towarde
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:7932:35"/>him. This hath he alwais ſhewed, but now more then euer. You ſée how God hath lately bleſſed him, in deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vs into his hands, ſo as if his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine helpe ſhould once ioine with him, his diſcretion, valour, and dexteritie would ſet our ſpurres cloſe inough to our héeles. It is therefore moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for you to diſpoſe your ſelues to preuent the miſchiefe which God hath prepared for vs in the reencounter of theſe armies, the hazard whereof can not but redound greatly to the kinges loſſe: for if he get the victorie, it wil be with horrible ſlaughter of his ſubiects: and if he loſe it, his ſtate is gone, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall wee peraduenture hereafter finde ſuch fauor at the Conquerors hands as we would deſire. Take heede it fall not out with vs, as it did with the <hi>Tyrians,</hi> who refuſing the honeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition that <hi>Alexander</hi> offered, were afterward taken by aſſault and cruelly entreated: rather leade the way to theſe reformed in this godly work of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by offering vnto them ſuch vnion and concord as heretofore haue beene among you: or els follow their ſteps, who from the beginning haue cryed for, and deſired nothing but the way to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:7932:36"/>be ioyned againe vnto you, namely a <hi>Councell</hi> lawfully called, wherein all points of religion may be decided of the ſcriptures, and not by opinions: by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, not by rage: by the quietneſſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, not by the bitterneſſe of malice: neither alledge that, as is aforeſaide, that is done alreadie: for the Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> the firſt general after the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time within y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpace of thrée hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth yeares, was no preiudice to the calling of diuers other according to the exigents of the affaires, as the ſame of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> egainſt <hi>Macedonius</hi> biſhop of the ſame citie, who denied the diuinitie of the holy Ghoſt: of <hi>Epheſus</hi> againſt <hi>Pelagius</hi> &amp; <hi>Neſtorius</hi> biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> who denied the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of Ieſus Chriſt: of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Eutiches</hi> alſo a prieſt of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> who confounded the two natures of Ieſus Chriſt: the ſecond of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> againſt <hi>Anthemius</hi> biſhop of the ſame place, who denyed that the virgin <hi>Mary</hi> had brought forth Ieſus Chriſt Man &amp; God: to be briefe, many other generall Councels, often called. Beſides all which, our kinges haue alſo béene careful to call ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly for <hi>Fraunce.</hi> Vnder <hi>Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:7932:36"/>the firſt, there were two holden at <hi>Paris:</hi> ſeuen or eight at <hi>Orleance:</hi> two at <hi>Tours</hi> vnder <hi>Paule</hi> the firſt, and an other by the authority of <hi>Pepin</hi> againſt the <hi>Greekes,</hi> concerning the trinitie: vnder <hi>Adrian</hi> the firſt, and by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of <hi>Charlemaigne</hi> ſeuen at <hi>Magence, Reimes, Tours, Chalais,</hi> and <hi>Arles</hi> for the reformation of the ſtate of the Church: vnder <hi>Gregory</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authority of <hi>Lewis</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> méek, one at <hi>Aix</hi> the Chapel, wherein the ſuperfluitie of the Clargie was reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whereupon they grew to mutiny, &amp; procured the curſed reuolt of <hi>Lewis</hi> his children. Others haue there béene holden for the reformation of the Clar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie vnder <hi>Leo</hi> the ninth at <hi>Rheims:</hi> but ſince as the Popes authoritie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, the Kings diminiſhed, and ſo conſequently, diſorders were more tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated in the Church: and vnleſſe I be deceiued, of the corruption of maners, which euery one confeſſeth, and all hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories doe teſtifie, ſome part may haue crept euen into the doctrine, either throug ambition or couetouſnes of the Doctors: howbeit I alſo ſaid that <hi>Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane</hi> the ſecond came perſonally into <hi>Fraunce</hi> to hold the Councel at <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:7932:37"/>in <hi>Auuergne: Paſcall</hi> to holde that of <hi>Troy: Innocent</hi> the fourth to hold that of <hi>Lyons: Gregory</hi> the tenth to hold another in the ſame towne: as for <hi>Clement</hi> the fifth, he held his ſeat at <hi>Auignion,</hi> and celebrated the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Councel at <hi>Vienna</hi> in <hi>D'Aulphin.</hi> Afterwarde <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> the Emperor procured the holding of the Councel of <hi>Conſtance</hi> vnder <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>23.</hi> who was there depoſed. That of <hi>Baſill</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fourth who alſo, was there depoſed. That of <hi>Florence</hi> vnder <hi>Amedee</hi> or <hi>Felix</hi> the fifth. After all theſe there was one holden at <hi>Orle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> by the French Church againſt <hi>Pius</hi> the ſecond, who would haue abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed the <hi>Pragmaticall ſanction,</hi> as an hereſie which was but the dependance of the Councell of <hi>Baſill:</hi> an other at <hi>Tours</hi> againſt Pope <hi>Iuly</hi> the ſecond: an other at <hi>Lions</hi> by king <hi>Lewis</hi> the twelfth, &amp; the laſt at <hi>Trent</hi> afore men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. You ſée then my M. whether the firſt Councels were euer any law to the ſecond, the ſecond to the third, &amp; ſo forth as néed hath required. It is w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> the Church as with our bodies: if the bodie be ſicke, we muſt call the phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: if the Church be diſeaſed, we muſt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:7932:37"/>haue recourſe to the Councels, &amp; therin to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſult vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient remedies:</p>
            <p>But as it is not enough to haue once heard the Phiſitions opinion, but that according as the ſickneſſe encreaſeth, we muſt alſo haue ſtill recourſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: euen ſo muſt we vpon euerie occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on gather againe togither theſe ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Phiſitions of whom the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell muſt conſiſt, heare them without paſſion, commaund the diſeaſed to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, take reaſon in paiment, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuere to the ende in their firme reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. If the Church fall againe, wée muſt again call for theſe helpes to raiſe it vp, and ſo continually without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion vnto the end of the world, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the head of the Church ſhall holde his laſt Councell. Not that I would at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie word ſo trouble the Biſhops, or for the leaſt ache that may happen to our fingers end: but when the miſchief is vniuerſall, we muſt ſéeke the like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie. The Gréeke and Latine Church met fouretéene or fiftéene times to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude vpon an agréement: and albeit there reſted ſome difficultie, as yet there is, they neuertheleſſe neuer denounced warre each to other. There are nous but theſe reformed who haue ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:7932:38"/>vp all iniurie, in being debarred this ſoueraigne ſalue of reunion by a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell: I ſaie by one onely Councell, ſo farre are wee from graunting them many vpon neceſſitie. What can you terme this refuſall but ſtomake and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury. I would neuer haue thought they had had ſo much reaſon on their ſide. Wee haue wiſhed to arme the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> yea euen by force to compell him, rather then to ſtraine our ſelues to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſcend to ſo iuſt a demand. Touch me hath he ſaid to you if I be ignorant, and ye haue beaten him: hee hath har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened to you and ye haue ſtopped your mouthes: hée hath aſked you the way to heauen and yee haue ſtopped your eares. Your voice hath béen like to the voice of the <hi>Edomites,</hi> at the taking of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and all men haue heard you cry: on, ſacke, blood and fire. Out of your ſchooles as out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Troyan</hi> horſe haue ſodenly ſtepped forth theſe armies wherewith ye haue threatened this prince, yea they haue béen almoſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his armie before he hath béen readie to beate them of. This is a matter in freſh remembrance, and euery man can beare me witneſſe of the truth: the more I conſider it, the better ground doe I And for their taking of armes, yea there
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:7932:38"/>was neuer thing more iuſt then their procéedings. He defendeth himſelfe, but being aſſailed. He purſueth vs, but after he had reculed: hée taketh reuenge, but being iniured. He calleth the ſtranger, but when his haue driuen him away. Who then can miſlike his reſolution after ſo long patience? Wee ſhoote at him, who can then blame him for loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to himſelfe? Wee vndermine his honours and dignities, why then ſhall not hee rampier them vp againe? Oh, how deare will theſe brawles bee to <hi>France?</hi> all the forces of the world doe ſéeme on euerie ſide to fall vpon vs for our confuſion and diſſipation. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I can comprehend the domeſticall, yet doe I more feare the forrein, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> who by little and little groweth licorous of the delicaties of our country. Long haue they enuied vs, neither wil they obſerue the league vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till their enuy be contented. For theſe enemies of the peace of <hi>France,</hi> where they can by nothing but by vniuſtice &amp; violence, will make a good peniworth of ſo much as ſhall be at their diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to caſt it into the throates of theſe <hi>Marans,</hi> in hope ſtill to retaine the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioritie. But that nation is ſubtill e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:7932:39"/>to vſe this meane to their owne aduantage, and as within theſe fewe yéeres while they haue had a faire wind they haue not accuſtomed themſelues to ſerue, ſo wil it be hard for the French men to eſcape their dominion vnleſſe they looke the ſooner to it. And this is it that king <hi>Philip</hi> barketh at: this it is that he wanteth to accompliſh his moſt large conqueſts: this is the floure that hee wanteth in his noſegaie: hee hath long ſince caſt an eie at it, and now is the time that hée will ſtretch foorth his hand to take it. And indéed <hi>France</hi> is now but an Antes neſt of Eſpaniolized perſons, that is to ſay, of Traitors and periures to <hi>France:</hi> their cofers doe ſwel with Spaniſh Duccats, and theſe wretches are not aſhamed for readie mony to ſell the libertie which our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſo painfully purchaſed, yea vnles God breake off the purpoſes of theſe corrupt perſons, we ſhal in the end find our ſelues the Turkes Ieniſſaries and this Pirats ſlaues. If it were as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to ſhake off the yoake as to take it, I could wiſh theſe goodly perturbers a while to try the tiranny of theſe <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires,</hi> and ſo I hope we ſhould ſoone ſée them runne back to their franchize: but
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:7932:39"/>it lieth is vpon to kéep them from that, yea from making euen the leaſt motion that may be: for theſe Foxes wil eaſily ſet faſt whereſoeuer they can but reach their nailes, &amp; all the bodie where they ſet their féete. And ſith part of vs do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie ſtoope vnder the burthen, I hope that God will ſo ſtrengthen the king of <hi>Nauar,</hi> and all the princes of the blood, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> theſe ſtaruelings ſhall looſe but their longing. Alſo if the princes do but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their braue exploits, I wold wiſh theſe pernitious Counſailors of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtate to put vp their pipes &amp; ſounde their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trait betimes, leſt the night of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon miſhaps ouertake them. And as for you my maiſters I doe once againe beſéech you to take pitie of this miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble realme. Conſider of what impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance it is to kéepe a ſtranger armed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you: giue eare to the wofull cries of ſo many widowes, Orphanes, and friendles, laide deſolate by the warres. Meaſure not others miſhappes by your eaſe, neither vnder the pretence that the blowes touch you not, thinke that thoſe of your neighbors ſhould not moue you to compaſſion. If euer you loued this realme in her greateſt eminency, alas cheriſh thoſe ſmall beames that yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:7932:40"/>Reare vp the old walles of this building with all your power: ſuffer not theſe <hi>Eroſtrates</hi> to waxe noble in our aſhes. And behold the king of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre</hi> watcheth vpon the conſeruation therof, beware ye ſléepe not in your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, when carefully you ſhould looke for the meanes to make vs all to take reſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwéetnes of peace. Otherwiſe my maſters looke for nothing but Gods iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts againſt your hardned harts, and for the fire of your ſeditions which you haue kindled, the flame of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation which neuer will be quenched, alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like puniſhment as <hi>Chore, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> for going about to diuide the Lords Tabernacle. For my part I will get mée to my owne home, as into a ſafe port, from whence I may behold your ſhipwracke, and if in ſhort ſpace I can not ſée you diſpoſed to your ſafetie, and that by your induſtry theſe warres do continue, I proteſt to yéeld my ſelfe to theſe princes, to encurre like fortune as they, vntill they haue reaped the fruits of thoſe labors which you laie vpon them, which ſhalbe a peace crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with contentation, by the helpe of God, whom I beſéech, my maiſters, to enſpire you with his grace, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie to take pitie of his Church.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:7932:40"/>
            <head>The King of Nauars ſong after his victorie.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SInce that my hands in victorie,</l>
               <l>thy puiſsance (Lord) did know:</l>
               <l>My toong ſhall not in ſilence reſt,</l>
               <l>till glory thine it ſhow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That forces theirs did not abate,</l>
               <l>our courage ought at all:</l>
               <l>Did ſhew that thou didſt vs protect,</l>
               <l>whereby their ſtrength was ſmall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Their numbers great like duſt in skie,</l>
               <l>which winde driues here and there:</l>
               <l>Thine Angell did diſperſe abroad,</l>
               <l>ſo that we nought did feare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And thoſe who did their honour build,</l>
               <l>vpon my fall, whoſe pride</l>
               <l>All men adored, I ſoone beheld,</l>
               <l>diſtreſsed far and wide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which wonder ſtrange to conquere thoſe,</l>
               <l>before I ſeemed to fight:</l>
               <l>Doth ſhew that all our conqueſts comes,</l>
               <l>through thy great power and might.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For as the rage of furious waues,</l>
               <l>againſt the Rocke do breake:</l>
               <l>So did their forces through thy helpe,</l>
               <l>gainſt ours ſuſtaine the wreake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Their courage great, puft vp with hope,</l>
               <l>exceedingly did ſwell:</l>
               <l>Their pride did mount vnto the heauens,</l>
               <l>from whence their ruine fell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:7932:41"/>
               <l>The eye which blood and murther ſought,</l>
               <l>and throat which open laie</l>
               <l>To blaſphemy, full gorged is,</l>
               <l>with venome for their paie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My heart (O Lord) full ioyfull is,</l>
               <l>to ſee thy foes downe caſt:</l>
               <l>Who laide the giunes wherein them ſelues,</l>
               <l>were game and praie at laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They me purſued without a cauſe,</l>
               <l>but they ouertaken were:</l>
               <l>The knots of their deuiſes cut,</l>
               <l>and iuſt rewards did beare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So to repreſse the like outrage,</l>
               <l>the Lords ſtrong arme we neede:</l>
               <l>Who faileth none which do him truſt,</l>
               <l>but paies the bad their meede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of time which brought our weale,</l>
               <l>through our deſert made ſhort:</l>
               <l>And God our cries did not neglect,</l>
               <l>though we did his in ſport.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherefore (O Lord) cry ſtill and pearce</l>
               <l>mine eares, vntill thy voice</l>
               <l>I heare, and learne thee to obey,</l>
               <l>in whom I may reioice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Giue ſtrength that in like dangers we</l>
               <l>amazed may not go:</l>
               <l>And as thou haſt begun ſo ende,</l>
               <l>each worke the end doth ſhow.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7932:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
